A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Grants, Accession 2015:115 FA1321
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Grants, Accession 2015:115
1979-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1321
17.23 Cubic Feet 50 boxes - 42 letter-sized document containers, 3 legal-sized document containers, and 1 oversize document container box (4 document containers of separated materials)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2015 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2015:115.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
Each folder title typically includes (1.) Name of Grantee; (2.) Project Name; and (3.) Grant Program Action Number. The Ford Foundation Program Area (ex. Peace and Social Justice, Media, Arts, and Culture, Overseas, etc.) associated with each particular grant, along with further description of the types of materials, can be found in the additional description note.
Each Ford Foundation Grant and the corresponding Grant File is identified by a unique Program Action (PA) number. PA numbers begin with the year a grant was made (2-digits), followed by a sequential number within that year (4-digits).
For example: PA 55-0123 was the 123rd grant made in the year 1955. PA numbers are often typed or handwritten on Ford documents in the following format: 55-123 (year)-(####). However, the Ford Foundation's grants database (LINKS) uses an 8-digit format for PA numbers: 05500123 (0YY#####).
Beginning in the 1970s the 4th digit in the 8-digit PA number was used to encode at least three different types of Ford grants:
1. 0YY5#### = Delegated Authority Grants (DAG) / Delegated Authority Projects (DAP)
2. 0YY6#### = Grants to Individuals
3. 0YY9#### = Foundation Administered Projects (FAP)
After the year 2000 a "1" is used as the first digit in the 8-digit PA number to signify the 21st century. For example, the 123rd grant made in 2012 would be PA number 11200123.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains press clippings, photographs, slides, digital media, brochures, and other ephemera related to various Ford Foundation grants from the 1990s to the 2000s. These materials were retained as part of a grant's attachments file. More information about individual grants can be found in the Ford Foundation's microfilmed grant records collections.
Related Materials
For further descriptions of Ford Foundation grants in this collection, please refer to the following findng aids (arranged alphabetically):
FA732A Ford Foundation records, Grants, A-B
FA732B Ford Foundation records, Grants, C-D
FA732C Ford Foundation records, Grants, E-G
FA732D Ford Foundation records, Grants, H-K
FA732E Ford Foundation records, Grants, L-N
FA732F Ford Foundation records, Grants, O-R
FA732G Ford Foundation records, Grants, S-Thel
FA732H Ford Foundation records, Grants, Them-Tw
FA732I Ford Foundation records, Grants, U-Z
Separated Materials
Special format items have been separated from the body of the collection and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation -- Overseas Offices; Arts and culture; Community development; Democracy -- Global; Education, Higher; Human rights; Social justice; Theater; Youth
- Grants, 1979-2007; 1
  - Alabama Shakespeare Festival (ASF) - Theater - Slides and Photos: ASF/Scarsbrook - 10000823, 2001; 2015:115:001 - 2015:003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Notes from original folder: #2 ND/ND; Education, Media, Arts and Culture (EMAC)/Education, Knowledge, and Religion (EKR)
    - Alabama Shakespeare Festival slides, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Item 2015:115:001)
      Slides from Twelfth Night, A Month in the Country, A Man for All Seasons, A Night in Tunisia, Godspell, Holiday Memories, Guys and Dolls, Blues for an Alabama Sky, Scapin, A Midsummer Night's Dream, The Negro of Peter the Great, and Relative Values
      Separated Materials
      Special format items have been separated from the above listed file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
    - Alabama Shakespeare Festival slides, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Item 2015:115:002)
      Slides from And Tender Ladies, Richard III, Cinderella, Julius Caesar, King John, Beehive, A Doll's House, A Midsummer Night's Dream, The Negro of Peter the Great, Blues for an Alabama Sky, An Ideal Husband, Driving Miss Daisy
    - Aaronville Dawning and The Venus de Milo is Armed photos, undated (Box 1, Item 2015:115:003)
  - University of Southern California - Center for Higher Education Policy Analysis: Students of College Preparation Programs in Postsecondary Institutions: Improving Program Effectiveness and Student Achievement - 09701217, 2002 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Education, Media, Arts and Culture (EMAC)/Education, Knowledge, and Religion (EKR)
  - University of Southern California - Center for Higher Education Policy Analysis: Students of College Preparation Programs in Postsecondary Institutions: Improving Program Effectiveness and Student Achievement, Addendum I - 09701217 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - University of Southern California - Center for Higher Education Policy Analysis: Students of College Preparation Programs in Postsecondary Institutions: Improving Program Effectiveness and Student Achievement, Addendum II - 09701217, 2002 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - On Purpose Associates - White Paper: Lessons Learned from the Ford Foundation's Corporate Involvement Initiative, Peter Plastrik, John Cleveland, and Richard Anderson - 09901766, 2001 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Evaluation of the Development Finance and Economic Security (DFES)/Community Development (CD)
  - The Ghana Center for Democratic Development - Financial Statements - 10200972, 2002 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education - A Summit for Women of Color Administrators and Faculty in Higher Education, Validating Our Strengths: Exercising Leadership Through Participation and Achievement, Providence, Rhode Island - 10450266, 2004 November 4-6; Digital media in folder - CD-RW - Enclosure 3 - A Summit for Women of Color Administrators and Faculty in Higher Education - Validating Our Strengths: Exercising Leadership Through Participation and Achievement, 2004 November 4-6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Note from original folder: Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom (KCF)/Education, Sexuality, Religion (ESR)
    American Council on Education - The Seventh Meeting in the Classic Series Confluence of Leading Administrators and Scholars Sharing Intellectual Community
    - CD - Enclosure 3 - A Summit for Women of Color Administrators and Faculty in Higher Education - Validating Our Strengths: Exercising Leadership Through Participation and Achievement, 2004 November 4-6; CD-RW (Box 1, Item 2015:115:004)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - The African Marketplace, Inc. - 09900723, 2002-2003; Digital media in folder - 2 CD-ROMs - African American Los Angeles - "Celebrating the History and Spirit of African American Heritage" and African American Los Angeles: Celebrate the History and Spirit of African American Heritage (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    Education, Media, Arts and Culture (EMAC)
    Includes: The Super Festival, Salvador-Bahia-Brazil; Global African Diaspora Cinema Symposium 2002; Rethinking Cultural Entrepreneurship Training: The Case of Cultural Entrepreneurship Development Program (CEDP), Karen D. Peters, 2003; Guide to Pan-African Cultural Markets, Professional Networks and Research Resources, Kira Breton, 2003
    Search Results for the Guide to Pan-Africancultural Markets, Professional Networks and Research Resources: A Report to the African Marketplace, Inc., Research enacted and compiled by Kira Brereton, May 2003
    - CD-ROM - African American Los Angeles - "Celebrating the History and Spirit of African American Heritage", undated; CD-ROM (Box 1, Item 2015:115:005)
    - CD-ROM - African American Los Angeles: Celebrate the History and Spirit of African American Heritage, 2004 March 3; CD-ROM (Box 1, Item 2015:115:006)
  - University of the Philippines - Reproductive Health, Rights, and Ethics Center for Studies and Training - Mainstreaming Ethics, Gender and Human Rights - 09901244, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    Overseas
    Contains: Reproductive Health, Rights, and Ethics Center for Studies and Training - Mainstreaming Ethics, Gender and Human Rights: A Professional Enrichment Program Mid-Year Progress Report, July 2001-January 2002; Reproductive Health, Rights, and Ethics Center for Studies and Training - Mainstreaming Ethics, Gender and Human Rights: Annual Report
  - Massag Foundation - NEKI (Legal Defence Bureau for National and Ethnic Minorities) - Legal Defence Activity in Hungary - The Copies of the Bills 1-274 - 09801521, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    Peace and Social Justice (PSJ)/Governance and Civil Society (GCS); IR-5
    Folder 12) Copies of Bills 1-134
    Folder 13) Copies of Bills 134-274
  - The Adithi Team - A Report for the Period February to July 1988 - 08900167 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Adithi Team - South South Study, K. A. Srinivasan - 08900167, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Adithi Team - Correspondence with Photographs - 08900167, 1988 December (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Adithi Team - Adithi Facilitates Women in Development in Bihar in Eight Key Economic Sectors - 08900167, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - The Adithi Team - Ahalya's Tear-Drops (Record of a Field Visit to Sitamarhi District) - 08900167, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Council for Community and Education Partnerships - 10001544, 1999-2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Education Media Arts and Culture (EMAC)/Education, Knowledge, and Religion (EKR)
    Contains: Financial Management Manual; Imagining Our Future: A Listening and Visioning Session with Key Stakeholders Resources Manual; Developing a Public Policy Agenda for Promoting Access and Opportunity Through K-16 Education Partnerships: A Listening and Planning Session with Policy Stakeholders; Bylaw; Mission and Vision Statement
  - National Council for Community and Education Partnerships - Gaining Early Awareness and Readiness for Undergraduate Programs (GEAR UP) - 10001544, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    Contains: Folder 22.) GEAR UP Workshop Agendas and Content Slides for Presentations; Folder 23.) GEAR UP for College: Creating Hope in High-Poverty Schools; Gear Up National Leadership Summit 2003; Grant-related correspondence; Information Technology Policy Manual
  - National Youth Employment Coalition - 10000912, 2002-2004 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Contains: 1.) Strengthening Collaboration Between Higher Education and Communities: Lessons Shared by Community Partners in Service Learning, A Campus-Community Dialogue Series Publication Indiana Campus Compact; 2.) Tell the Story: Achieving and Communicating Success, PEPNet Institute 2004; 3.) K-H-Community Partnerships: Working Toward Deeper Collaboration Between Schools, Higher Education, and Communities, A Campus-Community Dialogue Series Publication, Indiana Campus Connect
  - Policy Forum Report, Innovations in African Higher Education, Windsor Golf and Country Club, Nairobi, Kenya, Ford Foundation's African Higher Education Initiative - 10090012, 2001 October 1-3 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Corporacion Libertades Ciudadanas - 10450155, 2004 November (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Contains: Presentación Consejeros Del Presupuesto Participativo Comuna De San Joaquin Trayectoria Objectivos Propuestas; Texto Libro
  - Corporacion Libertades Ciudadanas - Informe de Actividades, Proyecto 2003014CHS - 10450155, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Oversize Poster - Presupuesto Participativo, 2004; 2015:115:052 (Box 3, Item 2015:115:068)
  - Yunnan Institute of Geography - Research Report on a Case Study of Bai Ethnic Community in Dongdeng Village, Er'yuan County, Yunnan Province (2 copies) - 10051839, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Mesas de Concertacion Locales y de Lucha contra la Pobreza: Impulsandolas desde las Mujeres - 09800639, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Informe: VI Reunion Del Comite De Coordinacion Nacional, Lima - 09800639, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Informe Comite Coordinador Nacional: III Reunion Nacional, Iquitos - 09800639, 2002 January 24-25 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Informe: V Reunion Del Comite De Coordinacion Nacional, Lima - 09800639, 2002 May 2-3 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Conference Materials - 09800639, 2001; Digital media in folder - 2 CD-Rs - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Mujeres por la Igualda Real - SPOTS, undated and Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Mujeres por la Igualdad Real - Monitoreos, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Includes: Dia Internacional De Accion Por La Salud De la Mujer, Peru 2001; Dia De La No Violencia Contra La Mujer; Los Derechos De Las Mujeres son Derechos Humanos; Carpeta Para Periodistas: Plataforma de Accion Mundial (PAM)
    - CD-R - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Mujeres por la Igualda Real - SPOTS, undated; CD (Box 4, Item 2015:115:007)
    - CD-R - Grupo Impulsor Nacional - Mujeres por la Igualdad Real - Monitoreos, 2002; CD (Box 4, Item 2015:115:008)
  - Environmental Law Institute - Mining and Communities - 10101484, 2001-2004; Digital media in folder - CD-R - Proyecto Comunidades y Mineria - "Mecanismos de Control Estandares en Actividades Extractivas para las Comunidades Afectadas por la Mineria", undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Assets/Community and Resource Development (CRD)
    - CD-R - Proyecto Comunidades y Mineria - "Mecanismos de Control Estandares en Actividades Extractivas para las Comunidades Afectadas por la Mineria" (Informes Memoria del Peru-Bolivia-Ecuador-Chile), undated; CD-R (Box 4, Item 2015:115:009)
      Environmental Law Institute, Oxfam America, Sociedad Peruana de Derecho Ambiental
  - Periodistas Asociacion para la Defensa del Periodismo Independiente - Libertad de Expresion en el Nuevo Escenario Argentino - 09900474, 2003 June (Box 4, Folder 36, Box 5, Folder 37-38)
    Folder 36: Informe Narrativo a la Fundacion Ford; Folder 37: Anexo Publicaciones; Folder 38: Anexo Publicaciones II
  - Periodistas Asociacion para la Defensa del Periodismo Independiente - Apoyo Institucional Para Actividades Que Promuevan la Libertad de Expresion en Argentina - 09900474, 2002 June (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Office of the United Nations - Making Progress - 10000885, 2003 December 22-2004 June 10 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC)
    An implementation report on the declaration and programme of action of the world conference against racism, racial discrimination, xenophobia, and related intolerance
  - WITNESS - 2001 and 2003 Reports - 10250485, 2001-2003 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Education, Media, Arts and Culture (EMAC) - Media Arts and Culture (MAC)
  - University of Michigan - Crossing Borders - 09701489, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    One piece of correspondence regarding storage of tapes from the 1998 Crossing Borders convening
  - Jobs for the Future - 09701395, 1998-2002 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Asset Building Community Development (ABCD)/Economic Development (ED)
    New Labor Market Intermediaries: What's Driving Them? Where are They Headed?, A Background Paper, Richard Kazis - Draft; Action Research Themes and Questions Employer Involvement in Workforce Development - Second Draft; Articles; JFF/WINS Demonstration Team: Annual Report on Skill Supply Chain Pilot Testing
  - Lewis & Clark College/University of Oregon Asian Studies Collaboration - Thank You Letter - 09600264, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Ikom Workshops Photographs - 10050457, 2003 March 4-5 (Box 5, Item 2015:115:010)
  - Hungarian Civil Liberties Union - Photos, Brochures, and Program Agendas - 09800396, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - United Negro College Fund (UNCF) 1999-2000 Annual Report - 09801683, 2001 July (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Tshwaranang Legal Advocacy Centre - 10350645, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    Includes press clippings, USAID Report - Women, Culture and Narratives on Masculinity: Cases from Kwazulu Natal and Limpopo, and Rural Legal Education Manual Australian Government AusAID
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) - 09300584, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 48-49)
    Folder 48: Two copies of A Proposal Submitted to the Ford Foundation for the Education Challenge Grant; Folder 49: A Proposal for an Evaluation of the High School Career Academies Submitted to the Ford Foundation, and An Evaluation of the Impact of the High School Career Academies on Disadvantaged Students: A Proposal to the Ford Foundation AusAID
  - Common Cents New York - Correspondence and A Proposal to Build Programmatic and Organizational Capacity - 10251847, 2002-2005; Digital media in folder - CD - Common Cents Penny Harvest Program: A Journey in Pictures - www.commoncents.org, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - CD - Common Cents Penny Harvest Program: A Journey in Pictures - www.commoncents.org, undated; CD (Box 6, Item 2015:115:011)
  - University of California, Los Angeles - North American Integration and Development: Industrial Restructuring Under NAFTA and Its Impacts, Draft Book Manuscript, Raul Hinojosa Ojeda - 09701650, 2005 February (Box 6, Folder 51)
    Asset Building and Community Development (ABCD)/Community and Resource Development (CRD)
  - The Center for Voting and Democracy - 09851058, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Includes: Brief of The Center for Voting and Democracy as Amicus Curiae in Support of Plaintiffs-Appellees Kevin Perkins and Robert McCoy Urging Affirmance and Claim Democracy Conference, Washington, DC
  - Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund (MALDEF) - 09800949, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    Includes: Policy Issues for the Presidential Candidates in the 2000 Presidential Campaign; Redistricting Reports; Court Documents - Coalition for Humane Immigrant Rights of Los Angeles (CHIRLA); Sindicato de Trabajadores por Dia v. Yvonne Braithwaite Burke
  - African Film Festival Press Clippings - 10351847, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom (KCF)/Media, Arts and Culture (MAC)
  - Unity Conventions - Asian American Journalists Association (AAJA), National Association of Hispanic Journalists (NAHJ), National Association of Black Journalists (NABJ), Native American Journalists Association (NAJA) - 09701347, 1999-2004 (Box 7, Folder 55-56)
    Folder 55: Unity Convention Press Room Book; Folder 56: National Lesbian and Gay Journalists Association Program at Unity '99; A News Management Reference Minority Recruitment Directory, The Radio and Television News Directors Foundation; Unity 2004 Convention, DC
  - Yayasan Jaringan Epidemiologi Nasional - 10250867, 1999-2003; Digital media in folder - 2 CDs - Kumpulan Artikel - Konas Jen X, 2003 January-February 1 and Kebijakan dalam Kesehatan Reproduksi, Materi Informas Komunikas, Informasi, Edukasi, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - CD - Kebijakan dalam Kesehatan Reproduksi, Materi Informas Komunikas, Informasi, Edukasi, 2002; CD (Box 7, Item 2015:115:012)
    - CD - Kumpulan Artikel - Konas Jen X, 2003 January-February 1; CD (Box 7, Item 2015:115:013)
  - United Nations Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean - Autonomía O Ciudadanía Incompleta: Identidad e Historia del Pueblo Mapuche en Chile y en Argentina, Isabel Hernandez - 10151866, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - South Africa National Parks - Muckleneuk, Pretoria (ATT) - Voices, Values, & Identities 1998 Symposium - 09851724 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Kalamazoo Symphony Orchestra Music, Photos: John Lacko - 10000814, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Kalamazoo Symphony Orchestra - Photos - Artist-in-Residence Michael Wood, undated (Box 7, Item 2015:115:014)
    - Kalamazoo Symphony Orchestra slides, 1997, 2000 (Box 7, Item 2015:115:015)
  - University of the Philippines, Quezon City - Philippine Nonprofit Sector Project - Occasional Papers - 09800469, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Third World Institute of Ecological Studies - 10251660, 2000-2002; Digital media in folder - 2 CD-Rs - Encuentro Continental de Parlamentarios... (Box 8, Folder 62)
    Peace and Social Justice (PSJ)/Governance and Civil Society (GCS)
    Journal articles
    - 2 CD-Rs - Encuentro Continental de Parlamentarios..., 2002 October 29-30; CD-Rs (Box 8, Item 2015:115:016; 2015:115:017)
  - RAND - What Do We Know About Bringing Development and Demonstration Programs to Scale? - 10100169, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Polish Association of Legal Education - 09800397, 1995-2000 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    Includes: Constitutional and Legal Policy Institute (COLPI)/Polskie Stowarzyszenie Edukacji Prawnej (PSEP) Street Law Conference, Warsaw, December 6-10, 2000; 2 copies of Prawo Na Co Dzien
    - Polish Association of Legal Education Oversize Posters (2), 2000; 2015:115:053 (Box 8, Item 2015:115:069)
  - Human Rights Society of Maranhao - 10101962, 2001-2004 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    Includes: Sociedade Maranhense de Direitos Humanos Em Defesa Da Vida: Programa Construindo A Cidadania Ativa: Projeto Vida De Negro and Sociedade Maranhense de Direitos Humanos Centro de Cultura Negra Do Maranhao Projeto Vida De Negro: Relatorio De Atividades Desenvolvidas No Periodo De Janeiro A Dezembro De 2003
  - Educational Forum - Anexos - 10150759, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Educational Forum - Anexo 10: 2.3 Resumen de Noticias "Alerta Educativa" - 10150759, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Educational Forum - Anexo 12 - 10150759, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Council for Excellence in Government - Strategic Plan - 09701611, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 69)